A Guide to the Office of the President Special Records, the University and World War II, 1939-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Office of the President Special Records, the University and World War II 1939-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/3.491
This collection consists of 4,500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access is prohibited for ten years from the date of creation unless special permission is granted by the President's Office. Under the terms of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Sec. 2.1-343 (4)), the records of the President or other chief executive officer of any state-supported institution of higher education are exempt from the law's access provisions. Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
This collection is transferred to the library by the President's Office, East Lawn, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va. on 1978 February 3.
Scope and Content Information
The Special Records series is comprised chiefly of topical records files which are not part of the "standard" topical files set up each year to form the Office Administrative Files.
These special records files are often kept in the President's office for a longer period of time than the single fiscal year covered by the typical transfer of Office Administrative Files and often cover a date range of several years. Because of this, the Office of the President refers to these as "permanent" or "seldom used permanent files."
When the office retires these files, they are often transferred to the Archives with the yearly transfer, and beginning with the 1982 transfer (RG-2/1/2.821) the "permanent " or "special" records files have not been physically separated from the Office Administrative Files, but form a separate sub-series in the listing to each transfer.
Contents List
- Adjutant General School 1942 (Box 1)
- Aeronautics 1941-1948, 3 folders (Box 1)
- American Council on Education 1941-1943, 4 folders (Box 1)
- American Council on Education 1944-1945, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Army - miscellaneous 1942-1943, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
- Army - Meteorological Training Program 1942-1946, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Army ROTC 1945-1947 (Box 2)
- Army School of Roentgenology 1942 (Box 2)
- Army Specialized Training Program 1942-1946, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Aviation Medicine 1941-1947 (Box 3)
- British Universities Manpower Situation 1942 (Box 4)
- Engineering, Science and Management Defense Training 1940-1942, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Engineering, Science and Management War Training 1943-1945, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Inter-University Defense Programs 1940-1942 (Box 4)
- Medicine 1944-1945 (Box 4)
- Military - miscellaneous 1942-1944, 1946 (Box 4)
- Military Training 1944-1945 (Box 4)
- National Defense 1940-1943 (Box 4)
- Naval Flight Preparatory Program 1942 (Box 4)
- Naval Flight Preparatory Program 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps 1939-1942, 5 folders (Box 5)
- Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Navy - general 1945-1947 (Box 6)
- Navy Ordnance Research Laboratory 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Navy V-12 program 1943-1945, 4 folders (Box 6)
- Navy V-12 program 1945-1946, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies 1945-1947, 3 folders (Box 7)
- Office of Chemical Warfare Service 1944-1945, 1947 (Box 7)
- Office of Naval Officer Procurement 1942-1944 (Box 7)
- Office of Scientific Research and Development 1941-1942, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Office of Scientific Research and Development 1943-1947, 6 folders (Box 8)
- School of Military Government 1945-1946 (Box 9)
- Student Enlisted Reserve Programs 1942 (Box 9)
- Student Enlisted Reserve Corps 1943 (Box 9)
- U. S. Office of Education Wartime Commission 1940-1943, 5 folders (Box 9)
- War Department - miscellaneous 1941-1945, 1947 (Box 9)
- War Department: Office of Chief of Ordnance 1943 (Box 9)
- War Loan Program 1942-1943 (Box 9)
- War Manpower Commission 1942-1944 (Box 9)